Let's put Codeex CLI to the test by
recreating an app that I personally use
on daily basis. So I created this local
transcription app which converts sound
into transcription
in any text box that I click on. The way
this works is when I click a couple of
hotkeys, I will hear audio feedback.
Then I can transcribe. Click those
hotkeys again and the transcription is
supposed to be there. So, let me give
you a quick demo.
I want you to help me create a local
transcription app that is going to
transcribe my audio into any text box. I
want you to follow the PD I am going to
provide for all the features in this
initial version.
Okay. And this is actually realtime
transcription. It's using whisper base
model. So, it's a relatively small
model, but still it's pretty accurate.
So, what we're going to do is we're
going to select this new GPT5 CEX high.
I'm going to also show you how long this
is going to take. So, here we're going
to actually start the stopwatch. But
first, I want to point out the PRD that
it's supposed to use. So, use and then
we can just say PRDMD.
Now, I'm using the latest version of
GPT5 on high settings. This is the
version of GPT5
specifically fine-tuned or optimized for
coding in Codex CLI. Right now I'm using
the integration with VS Code. So let's
see how this is going to work. In terms
of what I want to build, I'm calling
this system. It's a running title. It
probably is going to change, but the
idea is that it's a standalone
application with a Python back end that
is going to be running on Apple Silicon.
We're going to use the MLX framework for
loading both the speech to text model
for transcription and later on LLMs
which is going to fix any grammatical
issues in there. Now, so this is a
highle P. I also provided code snippets.
So to make it easy, I wrote some code
which actually works and we're going to
see how good this new GPD5 codeex model
is. Okay. So I am going to probably open
source this model or this project at
some point. If you are interested, let
me know. There's going to be a box where
you can put your email for updates
regarding this project. And I'm also
working on a more advanced version which
going to have an LLM and some other cool
features. But let's send this. But
before that, let's start the stopwatch.
I just want to time how long this is
going to take and what issues we're
going to face. So this is going to be an
example of a real world application that
you can build with Codex CLI.
Actually Codeex integrated within to
within an IDE in this case. Okay. So
right now it's reading the file. Seems
like it has read the file planning
approach and inspecting repo structure
in the folder. There's only that prd
file. I'm going to come back when we
have something complete. Okay. So it
added a task list. So first one is
understanding requirements and design
module layout for verbby. Then implement
transcription recording hotkey and menu
bar. And then add supporting assets. So
pretty neat and I can actually see that
it's working. So it created this folder
with some initial code. I think this is
based on the code snippet that I
provided. So while this is working, this
new GPD5 codeex model is supposed to be
able to work independently for more than
7 hours at a time on large complex
tasks, iterating on its implementation,
fixing text failures and so on and so
forth, right? which is pretty incredible
especially that the number of tokens
that it can generate are dynamically
selected based on the complexity of the
task. For example, they say that if you
provide a very simple task relative to
GBD5, this is going to generate almost
90% less tokens for the 10th percentile
of the easiest tasks. Right? But when it
comes to the last 10 percentile in terms
of complexity, they found that it can
generate up to 100% more or double that
the GPD5 model generates. And that's the
reason I also want to track how long it
actually takes to create this app for
us. Okay, so it's already been 5 minutes
and we're still on the implementation
part. So the only concern that I have at
this point is that I don't hit my limits
on the plus account while it's building
this app. Okay. So it just completed the
first iteration or first implementation
and it took about 9 minutes in total. So
now it's time to test it and see whether
it's going to work or not. Okay. So
first we're going to create a new
virtual environment. I'm going to call
it codeex word v. And let's use Python
3.10.
Okay. Next, we're going to install all
the requirements. Let's see if it
actually created that. Yep, it's there.
All right. Time to see whether it worked
or not. So, we're going to run this.
Okay. I don't see anything happening
yet. It might be downloading the model.
Okay. So, I can actually see this that
started. This is a quick recording of
testing whether the transcription works
or not. The hot keys definitely do not
work. And if I stop recording, let's see
what happened. So, we ran into an issue.
I don't know if I can just copy this. I
think it has to look up the
documentation. I don't think it did it
on the first instance. So, here's what
we're going to do. I'm going to restart
the stopwatch and let's see how long
this is going to take. Okay, so it took
about a minute 45 seconds. seems like it
has updated the code. Now, one of the
common issues that I have found is that
normally if you use these coding agents,
they will pin different package versions
and that can cause some issues. First,
let's see if the hotkeys work. Okay,
they actually are triggering something
here. So, let's run this. This is a
quick test of the transcription
capabilities of this new transcription
model. Again, same issue. So, I think I
need to uh ask it to actually go and
look at the documentation. Now, this is
the part where you'll have a lot of back
and forth with the model or coding
agent. So, in this case, I don't really
see it using any fixed version for the
packages. So, one of the biggest issue
with codeex is that it by default cannot
access internet. That means it will not
be able to look up documentation. So,
for example, it says I couldn't hit the
docs directly. This environment has
network access lockdown. So I updated
the loader path based on what the
package exposes at runtime. I'm going to
try this one more time. Although I don't
really have high hopes, but let's see.
Okay, I don't think the hotkeys work.
No, that is fine. We're going to try to
start triggering it for him. This is a
quick test of the transcription
capabilities.
Now we're going to try to stop it. All
right. Okay. This time it actually is
downloading the model. Okay. So, some
progress. Good news. Perfect. It
actually worked. So, let's have another
test. But the problem is I actually have
to trigger it from here. The
transcription seems to be working. But
the problem is that I have to trigger it
by going to the menu bar and then
clicking start and stop transcription.
hot keys seems to be not triggering the
actual transcription pipeline.
Okay. And yeah, it worked. Okay. So,
let's send this and let's see if Codeex
can actually find a solution. By the
way, we are about 6 or 7 minutes in plus
the initial 9 minutes. So, let's keep
going. Okay, so seems like it has
implemented a fix, but now this time um
it switched
um the hot keys for me. So now it's
supposed to be command and shift. So
let's see.
Okay, so seems like the recording has
actually started and I also heard the
audio feedback which was pretty neat.
Awesome. Okay, this is pretty awesome,
right? So I think within 20 minutes we
have a usable system that I can use for
local transcription. So great progress
so far. Now what I want to do is I want
to add the ability to actually see which
model is being used in the menu bar. Can
you also show which model is being used
for transcription? Okay, this time when
it triggered the transcription, I did
not hear the initial audio, but it was
able to transcribe it. Now, we're using
the Whisper Small MLX, which is a pretty
decent model. I'm running this on M2 Max
with 96 GB of unified memory, but still,
it's really fast. All right. Okay. So,
we'll just restart this again. And if I
go here, I can actually see the model
that is being used. Really good. Okay.
Uh can you also add the stats? And this
should persist
across different sessions. So I want to
see how many words were transcribed, how
many key strokes were saved, and the
total duration that was saved during the
transcription process. This seems to be
correct. Let's keep going. Okay. So, it
seems like we have the new feature
implemented. So, I'm going to just clear
this, rerun this again, and then let's
see what happens. So, it actually
showing the stats here. Now, let's
trigger this. It seems like after every
transcription,
you are unloading the model and
reloading the model for next
transcription. Is this actually the
case? Okay, so transcription is correct.
Now if we go back we can see yeah so 23
words
141 keys. Okay this seems to be accurate
but let's see if this is the case. I'm
going to continue working on this but I
would say that I'm actually pretty
impressed. GBT 5 codeex on high setting
is a really good agentic coding tool and
I'll highly recommend to test it out.
I'm going to continue testing it and see
if I can figure out or find out some
issues. I have tried to replicate the
same app with multiple different coding
agents and they've been able to do it
with varying degree of success. But I'm
actually pretty impressed by this
because I think almost within 30 minutes
we have a fully functional app at least
the transcription found. Now what I'm
going to do is I'm going to try to add
the LLM part and then try to create a
standalone version of this. So stay
tuned for that video if you are
interested and also make sure you sign
up for the notifications if you are
interested in the transcription app.
Anyways, I hope you found this video
useful. Thanks for watching and as
always, see you in the next one.